Welcome to the first lecture on the course on programming data structures and algorithms
in Python.
Let's start with the basic definition of what we mean by an algorithm and what programming
is.
As most of you probably know, an algorithm is a description of how to systematically
perform some task.
So an algorithm consists of a sequence of steps which we can think of as a recipe
in order to achieve something.
So the word recipe of course comes from cooking where we have a list of ingredients
and then a sequence of steps to prepare a dish.
So in the same way an algorithm is a way to prepare something or to achieve a given task.
So in the context of our thing, a recipe was what we call a program and we write down
a program using a programming language.
So the goal of a programming language is to be able to describe the sequence of
steps that are required and to also describe how we might pursue different sequences of steps
if different things happen in between.
So the notion of a step is something that can be performed by whatever is executing
the algorithm.
Now a program need not be executed by a machine although that will be the typical context
of computer programming where we expect a computer to execute our steps.
A program could also be executed by a person.
For instance, supposing the task at hand is to prepare a hall for a function.
So this will consist of different steps such as cleaning the room, preparing the stage,
making sure the decorations are up, arranging the chairs and so on.
This will be executed by a team of people.
Now depending on the expertise and the experience of this group of people, you can describe this
algorithm at different levels of detail.
For instance, an instruction such as arrange the chairs would make sense if the people
involved know exactly what is expected.
On the other hand, if this is a new group of people who have never done this before,
you might need to describe the step in more detail.
For instance, you might want to say that arrange the chairs in eight rows and
put 10 chairs in each row.
So the notion of a step is subjective.
It depends on what we expect of the person or the machine which is executing the algorithm
and in terms of that capability, we describe the algorithm itself.
Our focus in this course is going to be on computer algorithms and typically these
algorithms manipulate information.
The most basic kind of algorithm that all of us are familiar with from high school
is an algorithm that computes numerical functions.
For instance, we could have an algorithm which takes two numbers X and Y and computes
X to the power Y.
So we have seen any number of such functions in school, for example, to compute square root
of X. So what we do in school is we have a complicated way to compute square root
of X or we might have X divided by Y where we do this long division and so on.
So these are all algorithms which compute values given one or more numbers.
They compute the output of this function.
But all of us who have used computers know that many other things also fall within
the realm of computation.
For instance, if we use a spreadsheet to arrange information and then we want
to sort a column.
So this involves rearranging the items in the column in some order, either
an ascending order or a descending order.
So reorganizing information is also a computational task.
And we need to know how to do this algorithmically.
We also see computations around us in our day-to-day lives.
For instance, when we go to a travel booking site and we try to book a flight
from one city to another city, it will offer to arrange the flights in terms
of the minimum time or the minimum cost.
So these are optimization problems.
This involves also arranging information in a particular way and then computing
some quantity that we desire.
In this case, we want to know A that we can get from A to B and B among
all the different ways we can get from A to B, we want the optimum one.
And of course, there are very, very many more things that we see day-to-day
which are executed by computer programs.
We can play games.
For instance, we can solve Sudoku or we can play chess against a program.
When we use a word processor to type a document or even when we use our cell
phones to type SMS messages, the computer suggests corrections in our spelling.
So we will look at some of these things in this course.
But the point is to note that a program in our context is anything
that looks at information and manipulates it to a given requirement.
So it's not only a question of taking a number in and putting a number out.
It could involve rearranging things.
It could involve computing more complicated things.
It could involve organizing the information in a particular way.
So these computations become more tractable.
And that is what we call a data structure.
So to illustrate this, let us look at a function which most of us have seen
and try to understand it algorithmically.
So the property that I want to compute is the greatest common
divisor of two positive integers m and n.
So as we know, a divisor is a number that divides.
So k is a divisor of m.
If I can divide m by k and get no remainder.
So the greatest common divisor of m and n must be something which is a common divisor.
So common means it must divide both.
And it must be the largest of these.
So the largest k such that k divides m and k also divides m.
For instance, if we look at the numbers 8 and 12,
then we can see that 4 is a factor of 8.
4 is a divisor of 8.
4 is also a divisor of 12.
Another divisor of 12 is 6.
But 6 is not a divisor of 8.
So if we go through the divisors of 8 and 12,
it's easy to check that the largest number that divides both 8 and 12 is 4.
So GCD of 8 and 12 is 4.
What about 18 and 25?
25 is 5 by 5.
So it has only one divisor other than 1 and 25, which is 5.
And 5 is not a divisor of 18.
But fortunately, 1 is a divisor of 18.
So we can say that GCD of 18 and 25 is 1.
There is no number bigger than 1 that divides both 18 and 25.
Since 1 divides every number, as we saw in the case of 18 and 25,
there will always be at least one common divisor among the two numbers.
So the GCD will always be well-defined.
It will never be that we cannot find a common divisor.
And because all the common divisors will be numbers,
we can arrange them from smallest to largest
and pick the largest one as the greatest common divisor.
So given any pair of positive numbers m and n,
we can definitely compute the GCD of these two numbers.
So how would one go about computing GCD of m and n?
So this is where we come to the algorithmic bit.
We want to describe a uniform way
of systematically computing GCD of m and n for any m and any n.
So here is a very simple procedure.
It's not the most efficient.
We will see better ones as we go along.
But if we just look at the definition of GCD,
it says look at all the factors of n,
look at all the factors of n,
and find the largest one, which is a factor of both.
So the naive way to do this would be to first list out
all the factors of the first number m.
Then list out all the factors of the second number n.
And then among these two lists report the largest number
that appears in both lists.
This is almost literally the definition of GCD.
Now the question is does this constitute an algorithm?
Well at a high level of detail,
if we think of list out factors as a single step,
what we want from an algorithm are two things.
One is that the description of what to do
must be written down in a finite way.
In the sense that I should be able to write down the instructions
regardless of the values of m and n in such a way
that you can read it and comprehend it once and for all.
So here it's very clear we have exactly three steps.
So we have three steps that constitute the algorithm.
So it's certainly presented in a finite way.
The other requirement of an algorithm
is that we must get the answer after a finite number of steps.
Now this finite number of steps may be different
for different values of m and n.
You can imagine that if you have a very small number for n,
there are not many factors.
If you have a very large number for n, you might have many factors.
So the process of listing out the factors of m and n
may take a long time.
However, we want to be guaranteed that this process will always end
and then having done this, we will always be able to find
the largest number that appears in both lists.
So to argue that this process is well defined,
all we need to realize is that the factors of m must be between 1 and m.
In other words, although there are infinitely many
different possibilities as factors,
we don't have to look at any number bigger than m
because it cannot go into m even.
So all we need to do to compute the factors of m
is to test every number in the range 1 to m
and if it divides m without a remainder,
then we add it to the list of factors.
So we start with an empty list of factors
and we consider in turn 1, 2, 3, 4 up to m.
And for each such number, we check whether
if we divide m by this number, we get a remainder of 0.
We get a remainder of 0, we add it to the list.
So let us look at a concrete example.
Let us try to compute the GCT of 14 and 63.
So the first step in our algorithm says
to compute the factors of 14.
So by our observation above, the factors of 14
must lie between 1 and 14.
Nothing bigger than 14 can be a factor.
So we start by listing out all the possible factors
between 1 and 14 and testing them.
So we know of course that 1 will always divide.
In this case, 2 divides 14 because 14 divided by 2 is 7
with no remainder.
Now 3 does not divide, 4 does not divide,
5 does not divide, 6 does not divide, but 7 does
because if we divide 14 by 7, we get a remainder of 0.
Then again 8 does not divide, 9 does not divide and so on.
And finally we find that the only other factor left is 14 itself.
So for every number m, 1 and m will be factors
and then there may be factors in between.
So having done this, we have now identified the factors of 14
and these factors are precisely 1, 2, 7 and 14.
So the next step in computing the GCD of 14 and 63
is to compute the factors of 63.
So in the same way, we write down all the numbers from 1 to 63
and we check which ones divide.
So again we will find that 1 divides, here 2 does not divide
because 63 is not even, 3 does divide.
Then we will find a bunch of numbers here which don't divide
and then we will find that 7 divides because 7, 9s are 63.
Then again 8 does not divide, but 9 does.
Then again there are a large gap of numbers which don't divide
and then 21 does divide because 21, 3s are 63.
And then finally we find that the last factor that we have is 63.
So if we go through this systematically from 1 to 63,
crossing out each number which is not a factor,
we end up with the list 1, 3, 7, 9, 21 and 63.
Having computed the factors of the two numbers, 14 and 63,
the next step in our algorithm says that we must find
the largest factor that appears in both lists.
So how do we do this?
How do we construct a list of common factors?
Now there are more clever ways to do this,
but here is a very simple way.
We just go through one of the lists,
say the list of factors of 14 and for each item in the list,
we check if it is a factor of 63.
So we start with 1 and we say it does 1 appear as a factor of 63,
it does, so we add it to the list of common factors.
Then we look at 2 and then we ask does it appear,
it does not appear, so we skip it.
Then we look at 3 and look at 7 rather and we find that 7 does appear,
so we add 7.
Then finally we look at 14 and find that 14 does not appear,
so we skip it.
So in this way we have systematically gone through 1, 2, 7 and 14
and concluded that of these only 1 and 7 appear in both lists.
And now having done this we have a list of all the common factors,
we computed them from smallest to biggest
because we went through the factors of 14 in ascending order.
So this list will also be in ascending order.
So returning the largest factor just returns the rightmost factor in this list namely 7.
So this is the output of our function.
So we have computed the factors of 14, computed the factors of 63,
systematically checked for every factor of 14 whether it is also a factor of 63
and computed this list of common factors here and then from this list
we have extracted the largest one and this in fact is our GCT.
So this is an example of how this algorithm would execute.
So if you were to write it down in a little more detail then we could say that we need to
notice that we need to remember these lists and then come back to them.
So we need to compute the factors of 14, keep it aside, we need to write it down somewhere.
We need to compute the factors of 63, write it down somewhere and then compare these two lists.
So in other words we need to assign some names to store these.
So let us call fm for factors of m and fm for factors of n as the names of these lists.
So what we do is that we run through the numbers 1 to m and for each i in this list 1 to m we check
whether i divides n, whether m divided by i has remained a 0 and if so we added to the list
factors of m or fm. Similarly for each j from 1 to n we check whether j divides n
and if so we add it to the list fm. Now we have two lists fm and fn which are the factors of m
and the factors of n. Now we want to compute the list of common factors which we will call
cf. So what we do is for every f that is a factor of the first number, remember in our case it was
14 for each f so we ran through 1, 2, 7 and 14 in our case. So for each f in this list
we add f to the list of common factors if it also appears in the other list. So in the other list
if you remember it was 1, 3, 7, 9, 21 and 63. So we compare f with this list and if we find
it we add it to cf. And having done this now we want to return the largest value in this list
of common factors. Remember that 1 will always be a common factor so the list cf will not
be empty so there will be at least one value. But since we add them in ascending order since
the list fm and fn were constructed from 1 to m and 1 to n the largest value will also be the
right most value. So this gives us a slightly more detailed algorithm for GCD. It is more or
less the same as the previous one except it spells out in little more detail how to compute
the list of factors of fm, how to compute the list of factors of n and how to compute
the largest common factor between these two lists. So earlier we had three abstract statements now we
have expanded it out into six slightly more detailed statements. So this already gives us
enough information to write our first Python program. Of course we will need to learn a little
more before we know how to write it but we can certainly figure out how to read it.
So what this Python program is doing is exactly what we described informally in the
previous step. So the first thing in the Python program is a line which defines the function.
So we are defining a function GCD of m, n. So m and n are the two arguments which could be any
number like any function it's like when you write f of x, y in mathematics it means x and y are
arbitrary values and for every x and y do something depending on the values that you
call the function with. So this says that this is our definition so def for definition
of a function GCD m, n. So now the first step is to compute the list of factors of m.
In Python we write a list using square brackets. So list is written as x, y, z and so on.
So the empty list is just an open bracket and a square close bracket. So we start off with an
empty list of factors. So this equality means assign a value. So we assign fm the list of factors of
m to be the empty list. Now we need to test every value in the range 1 to n.
Now Python has a built-in function called range but because of we shall see because of
a peculiarity of Python this returns not the range you expect but one less. So if I say
give me the numbers in the range 1 to n plus 1 it gives me numbers in the range 1, 2,
m, 1 up to the upper limit but not including the upper limit. So this will say that i takes the
values 1, 2, 3 up to m. For each of these values of i we check whether this is true.
Now percentage is the remainder operation. So it checks whether remainder of
m divided by i is 0. If the remainder of m divided by i is 0 then we will append i to the list fm.
We will add it to the right. Append is the English word which just means add to the end of the list.
So we append i to m. So in this step we have computed fm. This is exactly what we wrote
informally in the previous example. We just said that for each i from 1 to m add i to fm
if i divides n and now we have done it in Python syntax. So we have defined an empty list of factors
and for each number in that range we have checked if it is a divisor and then added it.
And now here we do the exactly the same thing for m. So we start with the empty list
of factors of n for every j in this range. If it divides we append it and now at this point
we have two lists fm and fm. And now we want to compute the list of common factors.
So we use cf to denote the list of common factors. Initially there are no common factors.
Now for every factor in the first list if the factor appears in the second list then
we append it to cf. So the same function append is being used throughout.
It says take a list and add a value. Which value? We add the value that we are looking
at now provided it satisfies a condition. So earlier we were adding it provided the divisor was 0
or the remainder was 0. Now we are adding it provided it appears in both lists for every f
in the first list if it appears in the second list added. So after this we have computed ff.
And now we want the rightmost element. So this is just some Python syntax which you will see
which says that instead of if you start counting from the left then the numbers the
positions in the list are numbered 0, 1, 2, 3, 4. But Python has the shortcut which says if you
want to count from the right then we count the numbers as minus 1, minus 2 and so on. So it says
return the minus 1th element of cf which in Python jargon means return the rightmost element.
So this is the rightmost element. So at this point it's enough to understand
that we can actually try and decode this code this program even though we may not understand
exactly why we are using colons in some places and why we are pushing some things.
So you notice that there are other syntactic things here. So there are for example you have
these punctuation marks which are a bit odd like these colons. Then you have the fact that
this line is indented with respect to this line. This line is indented with respect to this
line. So these are all features that make Python programs a little easier to read and
write than programs and other languages. So we will come to these when we learn
Python syntax more formally but at this point you should be able to convince yourself that this
set of Python steps is a very faithful rendering of the informal algorithm that we
wrote in the previous slide. So let us note some points that we can already deduce from this
particular example. So the first important point is that we need a way to keep track of
intermediate values. So we have two names to begin with the names of our arguments m and n.
Then we use these three names to compute these lists of factors and common factors
and we use other names like i, j and f in order to run through these. We need i to run from one
to n. We need j to run from one to n. Of course, we could reuse i but it is okay. We use f to run
through all the factors in cf. So these are all ways of keeping track of intermediate values.
The second point to note is that a value can be a single item. For example, m, n are numbers.
Similarly, i, j and f at each step are numbers. So these could be single values
or they could be collections. So there are lists. So fm is a list, fn is a list. So it is a single
name denoting a collection of values. In this case, a list, a sequence. It has a first position,
an exposition and a last position. So these are lists of numbers. One can imagine other
collections and we will see them as we go along. So collections are important because it
would be very difficult to write a program if we had to keep producing a name for every
factor of m separately. We need a name collectively for all the factors of m,
regardless of how big m is. So these names can denote single values or collections of values.
And a collection of values with a particular structure is precisely what we call a data
structure. So these are more generally called data structures. So in this case, the data
structure that we have is a list. So what can we do with these names and values? Well, one
thing is we can assign a value to a name. So for instance, when we write fn is equal to the
empty list, we are explicitly setting the value of fn to be the empty list. This tells two things.
It says the value is an empty list. It also tells Python that fn denotes a list. So these are,
there are two steps going on here as we will see. And the other part is that when we write
something like for each f in the list cf, this is implicitly saying that take every value
in cf and assign it one by one to the value to the name f. So though we do not have this
equality sign explicitly, implicitly this is assigning a new value for f as we step through
the list cf. So the main thing that we do in a Python program is to assign values to names.
And having assigned a value, we can then modify the value. For instance, every time
we find a new factor of n, we do not want to throw away the old factor. We want to take
the existing list fn and we want to add it. So this function append for instance,
modifies the value of the name fn to a new name, which takes the old name and sticks an i at the
end of it. So more generally, we could have a number and we could want to replace it by two
times a number. So we might have something like i is equal to two times i. So star stands for
multiplication. This does not mean that i is equal to two times i arithmetically,
because obviously unless i is zero, i cannot be equal to two times itself. What this means is take
the current value of i multiplied by two and assign it to i. So we will see this as we go along. But
assignment can either assign a completely new value or it could update the value using the
old value. So here we are taking the old value of the function of the list fn and we are
appending a value to it and getting a new value of fn. The other part that we need to note
is how we execute steps. So as we said at the beginning of today's lecture,
a program is a sequence of steps but we do not just execute a sequence of steps from
beginning to end blindly. Sometimes we have to do the same thing again and again. For instance,
we have to check for every possible factor from 1 to m if it divides m and then put it in the
list. So some steps are repeated, we do something for example here for each item in a list
and some steps are executed only if the value that we are looking at meets a particular condition.
So when we say something like if m percent i is zero, if the remainder of m divided by zero then
append, so the step append i to fm, the factors of m, this happens only if i matches
the condition that it's a factor of m. So we have repeated steps, same thing done again and again
and we have conditional steps, something which is done only if a particular condition holds.
So we will stop here. So this example should show you that
programs are not very different from what we know intuitively. It's only a question of
writing them down correctly and making sure that we keep track of all the intermediate
values and steps that we need as we go along so that we don't lose things.
We will look at this example in more detail as we go along and try to find other ways
of writing it and examine other features but essentially this is a good way of illustrating
program.